<!--<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/5.0/rng/docbook.rng" type="xml"?>-->
<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.1.2//EN"
          "http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.1.2/docbookx.dtd">
<article lang="en">
  <articleinfo>
    <copyright>
      <year>2010 - 2013</year>
      <holder>ALMA - Atacama Large Millimeter Array</holder>
      <holder>European Southern Observatory, 2002</holder>
      <holder>Associated Universities Inc., 2002</holder>
    </copyright>
	<revhistory>
	    <revision>
                <revnumber>1.0rc1</revnumber>
                <date>26 Sept 2013</date>
                <revremark>Updated documentation for APRC Tool release 1.0rc1</revremark>
            </revision>
	    
	    <revision>
			<revnumber>0.8</revnumber>
			<date>14 Sept 2010</date>
			<revremark>Documentation for APRC tool release 0.8</revremark>
		</revision>
	</revhistory>

    <authorgroup>
        <author>
            <firstname>Jorge</firstname>
            <surname>Avarias</surname>
            <affiliation>
                <orgname>NRAO</orgname>
                <address>
            <email>javarias@nrao.edu</email>
          </address>
            </affiliation>
        </author>
        
      <author>
        <firstname>Arturo</firstname>
        <surname>Hoffstadt</surname>
          <affiliation>
          <orgname>ALMA</orgname>
          <address>
            <email>ahoffsta@alma.cl</email>
          </address>
        </affiliation>
      </author>
      
    <author>
          <firstname>Rafael</firstname>
          <surname>Hiriart</surname>
          <affiliation>
              <orgname>NRAO</orgname>
              <address>
            <email>rhiriart@nrao.edu</email>
          </address>
          </affiliation>
      </author>
      
    </authorgroup>

    <legalnotice>
      <title>Legal Notices</title>
      <para>ALMA - Atacama Large Millimeter Array</para>
      <para>(c) European Southern Observatory, 2002</para>
      <para>(c) Associated Universities Inc., 2002</para>
      <para>Copyright by ESO (in the framework of the ALMA collaboration), Copyright by AUI (in the framework of the ALMA collaboration),All rights reserved.</para>

      <para>This library is free software; you can redistribute it and/or modify it under the terms of the GNU Lesser General Public License as published by the Free software Foundation; either version 2.1 of the License, or (at your option) any later version.</para>

      <para>This library is distributed in the hope that it will be useful, but WITHOUT ANY WARRANTY, without even the implied warranty of MERCHANTABILITY or FITNESS FOR A PARTICULAR PURPOSE.  See the GNU Lesser General Public License for more details.</para>

      <para>You should have received a copy of the GNU Lesser General Public License along with this library; if not, write to the Free Software Foundation, Inc., 59 Temple Place, Suite 330, Boston, MA 02111-1307  USA.</para>
    </legalnotice>

    <releaseinfo>
        This version of the Planning Mode Simulator / ALMA Programme Review Committee Tool user manual only applies to version 1.0rc1 of the software. Please refer to previous version in <ulink url="https://ictwiki.alma.cl/twiki/bin/view/Scheduling/PlanningModeSimulator"> this webpage</ulink>.
    </releaseinfo>
    <title>Scheduling APRC Tool</title>
  </articleinfo>

    <sect1>
	<title>Introduction</title>
        <sect2>
	    <title>Abstract</title>
	    <para>The ALMA Programme Review Committee Tool (APRC Tool) allows to simulate the execution
		of observation projects for one or more observation seasons and analyse the results of
		the simulation, as well as the distribution of projects with respect to several
		parameters. The APRC Tool uses the same algorithm that the online scheduling system uses
		to select the next scheduling block to run, the Dynamic Scheduling Algorithm, or
		DSA.</para>
	</sect2>
	<sect2>
	    <title>Scope</title>
	    <para>This document only covers the description and user manual for the Planning Mode
		Simulator and Scheduling internal data model. The explanation is throughout in this
		sense, but the DSA is not covered by this document. Please refer to "ALMA Dynamic 
		Scheduling Algorithm" by Jorge Avarias and Rafael Hiriart for more information on this matter. For more information and software download, please go the <ulink url="https://ictwiki.alma.cl/twiki/bin/view/Scheduling/PlanningModeSimulator">this webpage</ulink></para>
	</sect2>
    </sect1>
    
    <sect1>
        <title>APRC Tool and DSA Architecture</title>
        <para><xref linkend="fig:arch"/> shows the general architecture of the APRC and the DSA. The
            APRC integrates several data sources, depending on its configuration. These are shown in
            the left side of the diagram. The data sources used by the APRC are configured in
            $APRC_WORK_DIR/context.xml.</para>
        <para>The APRC (and the DSA) uses an HSQLDB work database to perform its operations. Most of
            the data retrieved from the data sources is loaded into this relational work database,
            where it is stored in tables according to the DSA Data Model. Most of the DSA
            functionality is implemented as operations over the work database. It is advisable to
            gain some familiarity with the DSA Data Model, as it is the main model involved in the
            current implementation of the DSA and future additions as well. A description of the
            Data Model is given in <xref linkend="sec:datamodel"/>.</para>
        <para>Both the input data sources and the work database are accessed through Data Access
            Objects (DAOs). These are classes that allows access to the data through uniform
            interfaces, hiding the specific details involved in getting the data and transforming it
            to a common representation. This allows to connect the APRC (and the DSA) to different
            but equivalent data sources. For example, weather information is retrieved from
            historical files during simulation, but it is acquired by actual instrumentation when
            the DSA runs in the online system.</para>
        <figure id="fig:arch">
            <title>Scheduling APRC Tool Architecture</title>
            <mediaobject>
                <imageobject><imagedata width="100%" fileref="APRCArch.png"/></imageobject>
            </mediaobject>
        </figure>
        <para>We are now able to describe how the APRC works. The APRC:<orderedlist>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Loads data from different sources into the Work Database. This tasks is
                        done by several Loaders.</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Instructs the Dynamic Scheduling Algorithm to run a simulation. The
                        simulation can be done for the entire configured period (typically 6 months,
                        an observation season) or step through just one SB selection. This last mode
                        is used mainly for development and testing.</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>When the simulation finishes, the APRC generates several reports. As all
                        the data is persistent in the work database, it is possible to generate
                        reports afterwards as well. Some reports that don't require a simulation run
                        (such as the distribution of SBs though frequency bands, for example) can be
                        generated as soon as the data is loaded.</para>
                </listitem>
            </orderedlist></para>
        <para>The different data sources integrated by the APRC are:<variablelist>
                <varlistentry>
                    <term>ATM Tables</term>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>Atmospheric model tables. These tables hold opacity and brightness
                            temperature for a range of frequency and PWV. These tables are included
                            as part of Scheduling subsystem (specifically in the DSA jar file), and
                            are loaded into the simulator only in full load command. From the
                            simulator point of view this data is considered static.</para>
                    </listitem>
                </varlistentry>
                <varlistentry>
                    <term>Weather Historical Tables/Weather Instrumentation</term>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>Historical data for several parameters (temperature, opacity, wind
                            direction, wind speed), for one year, with a resolution of 15 minutes.
                            The simulator includes default simulated default values similar to the
                            ALMA's site average weather.</para>
                        <para>This historical files are only used by the DSA when running in the
                            context of the APRC. When the DSA runs with the online system, this data
                            is retrieved directly from the instrumentation.</para>
                    </listitem>
                </varlistentry>
                <varlistentry>
                    <term>Light Project Files/APDM</term>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>ObsProposal, ObsProject and SchedBlock data. These two sources are
                            complementary. Light Project files are XML files with a simplified
                            structure (i.e.., simpler than the APDM) that contains only the
                            parameters needed by the DSA. This alternative source for project
                            information was primary conceived as a development and testing aid.
                            Light Projects are maintained in $APRC_WOR_DIR/projects. APDM entities,
                            on the other hand, are retrieved from the ALMA Archive XML Store.</para>
                    </listitem>
                </varlistentry>
                <varlistentry>
                    <term>Executive Data</term>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>Definitions for the Executives (i.e.., USA, Europe, Japan), and their
                            respective observation time percentages. Currently this information is
                            maintained in XML files stored in the $APRC_WORK_DIR/executives
                            directory. Currently the definition of the PIs and their executive
                            memberships are also defined here.</para>
                    </listitem>
                </varlistentry>
                <varlistentry>
                    <term>User Repository</term>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>The definition of the PIs will be taken from the ALMA User Repository,
                            an LDAP database that is used by the ALMA-OT for user authentication.
                            Currently is not being used by the APRC.</para>
                    </listitem>
                </varlistentry>
                <varlistentry>
                    <term>Observatory Characteristic DB/TMCDB/CONTROL Subsystem</term>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>The array configurations, and a definition of the hardware state
                            versus time is currently stored as an XML file in
                            $APRC_WORK_DIR/observatory. Some of this information will come in the
                            future from the Observatory Characteristic Database, which will also be
                            used by OBSPREP. When the DSA runs in the context of the online system,
                            this information is retrieved from the TMCDB and the CONTROL
                            subsystem.</para>
                    </listitem>
                </varlistentry>
                <varlistentry>
                    <term>Ph1M</term>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>The Ph1M tool maintains its own database to handle project and
                            proposal information such as their scores and ranks. The APRC tool can
                            load the scores and ranks directly from the Ph1M database. It can also
                            reload them on demand.</para>
                    </listitem>
                </varlistentry>
        </variablelist></para>
        <sect2>
            <title>Simulation Work flow</title>
            <para>The simulation is bound to the availability of the data in the Working DB. For
                this reason a very strict work flow is defined in the form of a state machine. This
                State machine is handled internally by the simulator and it is exposed to the user
                through the available actions at certain point of the simulation. <xref
                    linkend="fig:simStateMachine"/> shows the representation of the state machine
                defined for the simulation work flow. </para>
            <figure id="fig:simStateMachine">
                <title>Simulation state machine</title>
                <mediaobject>
                    <imageobject>
                        <imagedata width="100%" fileref="SimulatorStateMachine.png"/>
                    </imageobject>
                </mediaobject>
            </figure>
            <para>The following is a brief summary of each state:
                <variablelist>
                    <varlistentry>
                        <term>Start</term>
                        <listitem>
                            <para> This is the initial state of the simulator, when no data has been
                                loaded yet into the working DB. Usually this state is reach only
                                after deleting manually from disk the working DB. </para>
                        </listitem>
                    </varlistentry>
                    <varlistentry>
                        <term>Static Data Loaded</term>
                        <listitem>
                            <para> In this state only static data (e.g. Weather simulation data, PWV
                                interpolation tables, etc) are loaded into the Working DB. At this
                                point the simulator is not ready to use, hence loading projects,
                                executives and simulation dates are required. This state can be
                                reach doing a <emphasis role="bold">Clean</emphasis> after a
                                simulation has been completed. </para>
                        </listitem>
                    </varlistentry>
                    <varlistentry>
                        <term>Dynamic Data Loaded</term>
                        <listitem>
                            <para> In this state static and dynamic data (e.g. Projects, Executive
                                Observation cycle, etc) has been already loaded into the Working DB.
                                In this state the simulator is ready to start. This state can be
                                reach doing a <emphasis role="bold">Full Load</emphasis> or a
                                    <emphasis role="bold">Load</emphasis> after a Clean. </para>
                        </listitem>
                    </varlistentry>
                    <varlistentry>
                        <term>Simulation Completed</term>
                        <listitem>
                            <para> In this state the simulation has already saved the information
                                required to generate all the reports. Since the simulation is
                                already completed (and the <emphasis role="bold">Run
                                    Simulation</emphasis> command has been completed), the only
                                action possible is to clean the dynamic data, and then start a new
                                simulation using fresh loaded projects. </para>
                        </listitem>
                    </varlistentry>
                    
                </variablelist>
                
            </para>
            
        </sect2>
        
    </sect1>
    <sect1 id="sec:aprc_tool">
        <title >The APRC Tool </title>
        <para>The APRC Tool works with two different directories: the APRC distribution directory,
            usually the <emphasis role="italic">aprc</emphasis> directory in the distribution
            tarball; and the APRC work directory, pointed by $APRC_WORK_DIR and set as default to
                <emphasis role="italic">aprc/work_dir</emphasis>.</para>
        <para>All the functionalities of the APRC Tool are available through the WebUI.  In the past
            a Command Line Interface (CLI) was provided, but due the lack of use and resources to
            maintain it has been deprecated. However it still available but unsupported.</para>
        <para>The APRC distribution directory contains all the executables, libraries and scripts
            needed to run the APRC. It contains the following subdirectories and files:<variablelist>
                <varlistentry>
                    <term>work_dir/</term>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>Global configurations for the APRC tool. One of the important files
                            here is the scheduling.properties which sets the Scheduling DSA policies
                            to load.</para>
                    </listitem>
                </varlistentry>
                <varlistentry>
                    <term>doc/</term>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>Documentation.</para>
                    </listitem>
                </varlistentry>
                <varlistentry>
                    <term>lib/</term>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>Java and WebUI libraries.</para>
                    </listitem>
                </varlistentry>
                <varlistentry>
                    <term>logs/</term>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>Contains the log output generated during the execution of the
                            simulation. Every time that the simulator is started it will create a
                            new log file.</para>
                    </listitem>
                </varlistentry>
                <varlistentry>
                    <term>README</term>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>The README file with important information related to the current APRC
                            Tool distribution.</para>
                    </listitem>
                </varlistentry>
                <varlistentry>
                    <term>pmsLauncher.jar</term>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>This special jar file contains an embedded version of jetty servlet
                            engine and all their dependencies to start the WebUI as simple as
                            possible. </para>
                    </listitem>
                </varlistentry>
                <varlistentry>
                    <term>test_array_configs.txt</term>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>This is an example of how the arrays configuration file has to be
                            created. </para>
                    </listitem>
                </varlistentry>
                <varlistentry>
                    <term>testPolicy.xml</term>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>An example of a Scheduling DSA policy file. It contains a basic DSA
                            policy definition ready to be used.</para>
                    </listitem>
                </varlistentry>
                <varlistentry>
                    <term>start_simulator</term>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>This script will setup the $APRC_WORK_DIR environment variable and the
                            DSA internal configuration to use the  provided configuration files.
                            Then it will start the embedded jetty servlet engine and it will try
                            open your browser to the main page of the simulator running locally in
                            your machine (This will work on the official supported platform RHEL 5).
                            If it is not possible to open the browser it will show a message
                            indicating the where to point your browser.</para>
                    </listitem>
                </varlistentry>
            </variablelist></para>
        <para>The APRC work directory, on the other hand, contains the datasets, the HSQLDB Work
            database, and other specific configurations. Its contents are:<variablelist>
                <varlistentry>
                    <term>aprc-config.xml</term>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>Several configuration parameters, such as the name of the directories
                            below, the Spring context file to use, and other parameters such as the
                            Executive grades and the array center location.</para>
                    </listitem>
                </varlistentry>
                <varlistentry>
                    <term>scheduling.properties</term>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>This file is used to configure the working DB backend to be used
                            within the APRC Tool. Also is used to configure which DSA Scheduling
                            Policy file will be loaded when the APRC Tool starts.</para>
                    </listitem>
                </varlistentry>
                <varlistentry>
                    <term>archiveConfig.properties</term>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>If the ALMA Archive DAO will be used to import projects, then this
                            file must be configured properly to get the connection to the ALMA
                            Archive. This works only inside ALMA JAO network. </para>
                    </listitem>
                </varlistentry>
                <varlistentry>
                    <term>executives/</term>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>As discussed above, this directory holds Executive data files.</para>
                    </listitem>
                </varlistentry>
                <varlistentry>
                    <term>observatory/</term>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>As discussed above, this directory holds Observatory data
                            files.</para>
                    </listitem>
                </varlistentry>
                <varlistentry>
                    <term>projects/</term>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>As discussed above, this directory holds Light Project data
                            files.</para>
                    </listitem>
                </varlistentry>
                <varlistentry>
                    <term>weather</term>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>As discussed above, this directory holds weather data files.</para>
                    </listitem>
                </varlistentry>
                <varlistentry>
                    <term>output/</term>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>As discussed above, this directory is used to output reports.</para>
                    </listitem>
                </varlistentry>
		  <varlistentry>
                    <term>reports/</term>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>This directory holds the reports created by the tool.</para>
                    </listitem>
                </varlistentry>
                <varlistentry>
                    <term>hsqldb/</term>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>This directory is used by the HSQLDB Work database. Deleting this
                            directory will reset the APRC Tool simulator to the start state. This
                            directory must be removed only once the Simulator has been shut
                            down.</para>
                    </listitem>
                </varlistentry>
            </variablelist></para>
        <sect2 id="sec:dsa_policy_setup">
            <title>Preparing a DSA Policies file</title>
            <para>The DSA Policies file is an XML Document based on an XML Schema. The documentation
                available for this XML Schema is available <ulink
                    url="http://www.aoc.nrao.edu/~javarias/scheduling/ALMA-10_4_0/DSA/"
                >here</ulink>. The XML Schema itself is available <ulink
                    url="http://www.aoc.nrao.edu/~javarias/scheduling/ALMA-10_4_0/DSA/SchedulingPolicy.xsd"
                    >here</ulink>. An example of this file is provided with the APRC distribution,
                check <xref linkend="sec:aprc_tool"/> for more details. </para>
            <para>The DSA Policy file to load at APRC Tool startup is defined in the <emphasis
                    role="bold">scheduling.properties</emphasis> file. The property <emphasis
                    role="bold">dsa.policy.file</emphasis> must be modified or added to point to
                your DSA policy file. It is recommended to put the absolute path of this file,
                however relatives paths to the root of the APRC tool (the aprc directory) are
                supported. The APRC Tool package distributed in a tarball shall come with a DSA
                policy file pre-configured already. </para>
        </sect2>
<!--        <sect2>
            <title>Running a simulation with the APRC CLI</title>
            <para>Running a simulation with the APRC usually involves the following steps:<orderedlist>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>Start the APRC work database.</para>
                        <screen>$ aprc start
Starting HSQLDB                        </screen>
                        <para>Currently the HSQLDB database that the APRC uses run in client/server
                            mode. This command will start the database server. It only needs to be
                            done once in a simulation session.</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>Load all the input files into the database.</para>
                        <screen>$ aprc fullload
sb.getPiName() = joe1@doe.edu
sb.getPiName() = joe2@doe.edu
sb.getPiName() = joe3@doe.edu
sb.getPiName() = joe4@doe.edu
...
</screen>
                        <para>This will load all the input files into the database, including the
                            weather files. Weather files are big, so it usually takes some minutes
                            for this command to complete. However, as loading the weather files only
                            needs to be done once, the command <command>aprc load</command> is
                            provided to perform subsequent loads. This command loads all the input
                            files <emphasis>excluding</emphasis> the weather files, and it is
                            usually much faster. An example will be given below.</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>Run the simulation</para>
                        <screen>$ aprc run
Running first update Tue Sep 14 14:52:33 CLT 2010
Finishing first update Tue Sep 14 14:52:35 CLT 2010
[2011-01-02T00:00:00] Array 1 created
[2011-01-02T00:00:00] Starting selection of candidate SchedBlocks for Array Id: 1
Size of criteria query: 124
Time used: 183 ms
Pre Selectors takes: 184 ms
Selection takes: 236
Start Calculations
6180
6228
Weather Calculations takes: 778 ms
Update takes: 1913 ms
Post Selectors takes: 0 ms
508,508,-0.46073496876365416
6180
ARRAY_CREATION End Date given by executor: Sat Jan 01 21:30:00 CLST 2011
SB EXEC END #: 508 Sen: 0.32644845140881207 ExecTime: 0.0
Step takes: 2266
[2011-01-02T00:30:00] Finishing Execution of SchedBlock Id: 508
[2011-01-02T00:30:00] Starting selection of candidate SchedBlocks for Array Id: 1
Size of criteria query: 118
Time used: 68 ms
Pre Selectors takes: 68 ms
Selection takes: 114
Start Calculations
6228
6276
Weather Calculations takes: 1 ms
Update takes: 18 ms
Post Selectors takes: 0 ms
1546,1546,-0.25186313880532074
6228</screen>
                        <para>The level of verbosity of the output to the console can be controlled
                            by the the options <option>-v</option>, <option>-vv</option>, and
                                <option>-vvv</option>, which configure the verbosity level to LOW,
                            MEDIUM and HIGH, respectively. The timestamps that appear in some of the
                            output messages is the simulation time, not the time of the computer
                            when the log was output. In the above screenshoot, it can be seen that
                            the simulation started at 2011-01-01T00:00:00, the observing season
                            start date, and the first SchedBlock finished its execution 0.5 hour
                            later.</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>When the simulation finishes, an XML file will be created in the
                            $APRC_WORK_DIR/output directory. This file contains the results of the
                            simulation. This file can be converted to HTML with the <command>aprc
                                report</command> command:</para>
                        <screen>$ aprc report help
[ahoffsta@ned APRC]$ aprc report help
Reports help
Usage: 
aprc report &lt;command>

List of Commands:
1:      Generate statistics report containing SBs per ALMA Receiver Bands.
2:      Generate result report (after run the simulation).
3:      Generate statistics report containing SBs per LST ranges.
help:   Show this help message.
[ahoffsta@ned APRC]$ aprc report 2
URL ofr xslt: jar:file:/home/ahoffsta/repos/SCHEDULING/PlanningModeSim/test/APRC/lib/alma-7.1/SchedulingPSM.jar!/alma/scheduling/psm/reports/general_report.xsl
</screen>
                        <para>This HTML file contains the results of the simulation.</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>It is possible to change the input files and run another simulation.
                            In order to do this, first it is needed to clean the database:</para>
                        <screen>$ aprc clean</screen>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>Now the input files can be modified. For example, you may be
                            interested in modifying the grade setups, in the file
                            $APRC_WORK_DIR/aprc-config.xml. Then the input files can be loaded
                            intothe database:</para>
                        <screen>$ aprc load</screen>
                        <para>This command doesn't load the weather files, so it finishes faster
                            than the <command>aprc fullload</command> command.</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>The simulation can be executed again. This process can be repeated as
                            many times as necessary.</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>When there is not more additional work to do with the APRC Tool. The
                            database server can be shutdown:</para>
                        <screen>$ aprc stop
Stopping HSQLDB</screen>
                    </listitem>
                </orderedlist></para>
        </sect2>-->
<!--        <sect2>
            <title>Importing scores and ranks from the Ph1M database</title>
            <para>The ObsProposal scores and ranks are managed in the Ph1M Tool. They can be
                imported into the APRC Tool work database by means of the <command>aprc ph1m
                    sync</command> command. This command iterates through the proposals in the work
                database and retrieves their scores and ranks from the ph1m database, updating the
                corresponding fields in the APRC database.</para>
	    <screen>
	    
	    </screen>
            <para>It is possible to inspect the scores and ranks in the ph1m database for the
                proposals stored in the work database by means of the <command>aprc ph1m
                    list</command> command. This command is useful to verify that the communication
                with the Ph1M Tool is working properly.</para>
	    <screen>
	    
	    </screen>
        </sect2> -->
    </sect1>
    
    <sect1>
        <title>The APRC Tool Web User Interface</title>
        <para>The APRC Graphical User Interface (or GUI), is a web application that allows access to
            the simulator functionality. It has the same capabilities as the CLI, and the ability to
            present multiple reports on screen. It uses the same technologies as the Ph1M tool, so it
            can be easily integrated with this application.</para>
        <sect2>
            <title>Architecture</title>
            <para>The architecture of the GUI follow a strict Model-Controller-View pattern. The
                framework used to achieve this pattern is ZK, which is a rich internet
                application (RIA) framework, that allows quick prototyping, but also has several
                enterprise qualities, such as automatic data mapping from user interface to
                controller, Spring framework and Hibernate integration, which are the
                same layers of frameworks that the scheduling subsystem has selected to develop the APRC
                simulator and the DSA. <variablelist>
                    <varlistentry>
                        <term>View</term>
                        <listitem>
                            <para>To construct the views, ZK provides ZUL, a language based on XML
                                and XUL, which are both widely used for user interface definitions.
                                It allows the developers to see exactly how the interfaces will look
                                (using a provided eclipse plug-in, called "ZK Studio"). ZUL is very
                                powerful, even allowing to embed Java code in the interface
                                definition. This functionality will not be used, as to better
                                separate the definition of the view, from the controller.</para>
                        </listitem>
                    </varlistentry>
                    <varlistentry>
                        <term>Controller</term>
                        <listitem>
                            <para>In the MVC pattern, controller is that piece of software that
                                handles the logic of the interface. The intention of this separation
                                (between view definitions, and logic) is such that views can be
                                easily changed, without much effort, enhancing maintainability of
                                the software, and allowing make quick changes easy. Java classes
                                that uses ZK's auto-mapping features allows transparent access to
                                view definitions. Even changes to it can be made from Java
                                code.</para>
                            <para>Controllers are automatically binded from the View definition. ZK 
                                allows intelligent and automatic binding between attributes defined at
                                view layer, with the controller actions. This helps to reduce coding time,
                                and provides a cleaner code.</para>
                        </listitem>
                    </varlistentry>
                    <varlistentry>
                        <term>Model</term>
                        <listitem>
                            <para>The model section of the MVC pattern, takes care of data handling.
                                Not only it's storage, but also it's processing. In this case, it
                                will be the APRC tool libraries, and the work database. This is
                                intended to reuse all the code between the CLI and the GUI, and to
                                allows the same tools, to have the same behaviour. All the specification
                                of this layer, corresponds to the same in <xref linkend="sec:datamodel"/>
                            </para>
                        </listitem>
                    </varlistentry>
                </variablelist></para>
        </sect2>
        <sect2>
            <title>Definition of Views</title>
            <para>Views are the user interfaces. This section contains a few examples of user views
                that are available in the GUI prototype. The prototype if not yet functional, but
                his has data access capabilities, and navigation is possible. The views are not yet
                settled, as this are only for technology-tests and to see if the selected stack of
                frameworks integrates correctly.</para>
            <variablelist>
                <varlistentry>
                    <term>Main window</term>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>This window (<xref linkend="mainWindow"/>) is the first screen a user
                            will see. The selected framework imitates desktop applications, so users
                            will not have to learn how to use a new application. The interface has a
                            window, that uses the whole web page. It has menu bar, where all
                            functionality can be found, according to the context of the selected
                            window. A predetermined set of tasks are set when there is no other
                            active window.</para>
                        <para> The menu entry "Simulation", allows to create new simulations, load
                            previous one, and save them. The menu "View" is set there to organize
                            the windows, when there are too many in the web page. "Help" entry has
                            links to this manual, download page, and information of the software
                            itself.</para>
                        <para> The large white-space is intended for window usage. As simulations
                            are created, ran and reports gets generated, different window will
                            become available and presented in there.
                        </para>
                        <figure id="mainWindow">
                            <title>Main window</title>
                            <mediaobject>
                                <imageobject><imagedata align="center" width="93%" fileref="psmWUI-1.png"
                                /></imageobject>
                            </mediaobject>
                        </figure>
                    </listitem>
                </varlistentry>
                <!--<varlistentry><term>New simulation window</term><listitem><para>When a new simulation is requested by the user, the window in figure <xref linkend="simConfigWindow"/> is presented. It is a form that has a series of necessary information, which is covered in previous section of this manual. To make things easier to the user, there is a "Default values" button, which completes the form correct and default values.</para><para>The form is automatically filled with default values, which will work create a working simulation. It will use a set or simulated sources in case of a standalone installation. In case of the ALMA STE deployment, it will be automatically configured to access Archive and Ph1m data.</para><para>This same screen is used to reconfigure previous simulations. This screen corresponds to editting <command>aprc-config.xml</command> file.</para><para>The basic panel covers configurations that are more likely to change, while advanced panel allows editing of configurations which corresponds to data sources path.</para><figure id="simConfigWindow"><title>Simulation configuration window</title><mediaobject><imageobject><imagedata width="93%" fileref="psmWUI-2.png"/></imageobject></mediaobject></figure></listitem></varlistentry>-->
                <varlistentry>
                    <term>Simulation window</term>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>When a simulation is created, different data sources needs to be
                            selected. Data sources are provided by the APRC tool back-end, and the
                            window depicted in <xref linkend="simWindow"/> presents to the user the
                            different options available.</para>
                        <para>At this moment, the simulator allows to choose the data sources
                            between the ALMA Archive DAO, which uses the ALMA Archive when is
                            possible (it requires to be in the ALMA JAO network and configure
                            properly the archiveConfig.properties file) and the XML Projects DAO,
                            which loads the projects contained in the $APRC_WORK_DIR/projects
                            directory.</para>
                        <para> The same window also has two side panels. The upper one gives the
                            status of the simulation, meanwhile the lower one, presents to the
                            users the most common tasks to execute.</para>
                        <figure id="simWindow">
                            <title>Simulation window</title>
                            <mediaobject>
                                <imageobject><imagedata align="center" fileref="psmWUI-3.png"
                                /></imageobject>
                            </mediaobject>
                        </figure>
                        <variablelist>
                            <varlistentry>
                                <term>Basic configuration</term>
                                <listitem>
                                    <para>This button is disabled and shall be removed in future
                                        versions.</para>
                                </listitem>
                            </varlistentry>
                            <varlistentry>
                                <term>Full data load</term>
                                <listitem>
                                    <para>This begins the process of data acquisition, storing it on
                                        a working, local database, for faster processing. This
                                        process load into the Working DB the static and dynamic
                                        data.</para>
                                </listitem>
                            </varlistentry>
                            <varlistentry>
                                <term>Load data</term>
                                <listitem>
                                    <para>As most of the time is spent loading weather data, this
                                        action only loads non-weather related data (dynamic
                                        data).</para>
                                </listitem>
                            </varlistentry>
                            <varlistentry>
                                <term>Clean data</term>
                                <listitem>
                                    <para>This action allows to erase all data from the working DB.
                                        If the user wants a clean start for a simulation, this
                                        action erases any traces of it from database. This action
                                        will delete only the non-weather related data (dynamic
                                        data).</para>
                                </listitem>
                            </varlistentry>
                            <varlistentry>
                                <term>Run simulation</term>
                                <listitem>
                                    <para>This starts the simulation, presenting <xref linkend="runSimWindow"/> to
                                        the user. Percentage is calculated in base of the start and end of the
                                        simulated observing season, and in which date the simulation currently is.</para>
                                </listitem>
                            </varlistentry>
                            <varlistentry>
                                <term>DSA Configuration</term>
                                <listitem>
                                    <para>This combo box contains the DSA Policies loaded into the
                                        APRC Tool at startup, these policies are read from the
                                        previously configured Scheduling DSA Policies file. Check
                                            <xref linkend="sec:dsa_policy_setup"/>. A policy must be
                                        selected to run the Simulation, at the beginning of the
                                        simulation the DSA will be configured using the selecting
                                        policy. By default the first policy is selected. The policy
                                        cannot be changed during the simulation execution.</para>
                                </listitem>
                            </varlistentry>
                        </variablelist>
                        <figure id="runSimWindow">
                            <title>Simulation window</title>
                            <mediaobject>
                                <imageobject><imagedata align="center" fileref="psmWUI-4.png"
                                /></imageobject>
                            </mediaobject>
                        </figure>
                    </listitem>
                </varlistentry>
                <varlistentry>
                    <term>Observatory and season configuration window</term>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>Pressing the button Review Configuration in the right-side panel will
                            open the window shown in <xref linkend="fig:array_season_config"/>. This
                            window contains all the array and cycle (season) configuration to be
                            used during the simulation.</para>
                        <figure id="fig:array_season_config">
                            <title>Arrays and cycle (season) configuration window</title>
                            <mediaobject>
                            <imageobject>
                                <imagedata fileref="psmWUI-array_season_config.png" align="center"/>
                            </imageobject>
                            </mediaobject>
                        </figure>
                        <variablelist>
                            <varlistentry>
                                <term>Simulated start date and simulated stop date</term>
                                <listitem>
                                    <para>These widgets will setup the start and end times for the
                                        observation season (cycle). The cycle may start before/after
                                        the first simulated array creation and may stop before/after
                                        the last simulated array has been destroyed.</para>
                                </listitem>
                            </varlistentry>
                            <varlistentry>
                                <term>Observation daily schedule</term>
                                <listitem>
                                    <para>The simulation can be configured to simulate the
                                        observation only during certain hours. The check box will
                                        enable this constraint, the user must setup the daily
                                        observation time interval. The times are in UTC. </para>
                                </listitem>
                            </varlistentry>
                            <varlistentry>
                                <term>Array Configuration</term>
                                <listitem>
                                    <para>Pressing the button Load arrays configuration will open a
                                        select file dialog box. The simulator accepts a text file
                                        containing a lite array configuration description, like the
                                        one included in the simulation distribution
                                        (aprc/test_arrays_configs.txt). Once the file is loaded and
                                        parsed correctly, the configuration overview of the cycle,
                                        including the arrays duration will be updated.</para>
                                </listitem>
                            </varlistentry>
                            <varlistentry>
                                <term>Configuration Overview</term>
                                <listitem>
                                    <para>These both time lines show a representation in different
                                        scales of the configured cycle and arrays duration according
                                        to the previous setup. The time lines are interactive, they
                                        can be moved pressing a mouse click on them and dragging the
                                        mouse while the button is pressed.</para>
                                </listitem>
                            </varlistentry>
                            <varlistentry>
                                <term>Save Configuration</term>
                                <listitem>
                                    <para>After the configuration has been completed. Pressing this
                                        button will save the configuration. The arrays
                                        configurations will be saved on disk in the directory
                                        (aprc/observatory). The cycle (season) will not be saved on
                                        disk, which means every time the data is loaded the start,
                                        stop and daily schedule must be manually configured.</para>
                                    <para>To cancel the changes close the window.</para>
                                </listitem>
                            </varlistentry>
                        </variablelist>
                    </listitem>
                </varlistentry>
                <varlistentry>
                    <term>Reports windows</term>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>The reports can be accessed from the top application menu. Two categories of reports
                            are available: pre and post simulation. Each menu entry presents a new window with the
                            select report. Examples of them, can be seen in <xref linkend="bandReportWindow"/>, 
                            <xref linkend="lstReportWindow"/>, <xref linkend="execReportWindow"/></para>
                        <figure id="bandReportWindow">
                            <title>Requested time per ALMA band</title>
                            <mediaobject>
                                <imageobject><imagedata width="93%" fileref="psmWUI-5.png"
                                /></imageobject>
                            </mediaobject>
                        </figure>
                        <figure id="lstReportWindow">
                            <title>Requested time per LST range</title>
                            <mediaobject>
                                <imageobject><imagedata width="93%" fileref="psmWUI-6.png"
                                /></imageobject>
                            </mediaobject>
                        </figure>
                        <figure id="execReportWindow">
                            <title>Executive percentage balancing</title>
                            <mediaobject>
                                <imageobject><imagedata width="93%" fileref="psmWUI-7.png"
                                /></imageobject>
                            </mediaobject>
                        </figure>
                    </listitem>
                </varlistentry>
            </variablelist>
        </sect2>
    </sect1>
    
    <sect1 id="sec:datamodel">
        <title>The DSA Data Model</title>
        <para>The DSA works internally with a data model conformed by a collection of Java classes
            that are made persistent (i.e.., its fields are stored persistently so the state of the
            class can be recovered) in the Work Database's relational tables. The structure of the
            tables is very similar to the Java data model, although classes in Java use inheritance
            and other object oriented constructs that don't exists in the relational model.</para>
        <para>The Data Model is divided in the following packages: 
        <itemizedlist>
                <listitem>
                    <para>executive</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>obsproject</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>observatory</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>weather</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>output</para>
                </listitem>
            </itemizedlist></para>
        <para>The source code can be found in the SCHEDULING/Common module.</para>
        <para>A class diagram for the executive package is shown in <xref linkend="exec_cd"/>. The
            main classes are ObservingSeason and Executive. There are two many-to-many relationships
            between these two classes, which are represented by ExecutivePercentage and
            ExecutiveTimeSpent. The first represents how much time a given Executive has for a given
            ObservingSeason. This class also holds the Executive remaining observation time. As a
            simulation is executed, ExecutiveTimeSpent records are created, recording the SBs that
            are executed and how much time should be charged to their corresponding
            Executive.</para>
        <figure id="exec_cd">
            <title>Executive package class diagram</title>
            <mediaobject>
                <imageobject><imagedata width="100%" fileref="Executive.png"/></imageobject>
            </mediaobject>
        </figure>
        <para>The relationship between a SB and an Executive is made though the PI. A PI can be
            related to more than one Executive. This relationship is represented in the PIMembership
            table. For convenience, this relationship is also maintained directly, as a link between
            SchedBlock and Executive.</para>
        <para>The obsproject package class diagram is shown in <xref linkend="proj_cd"/>. This
            package follows closely the APDM structure, although only the fields that are relevant
            for the DSA are used. Also, some additional classes and fields that are not present in
            the APDM have been added.</para>
        <figure id="proj_cd">
            <title>ObsProject package class diagram</title>
            <mediaobject>
                <imageobject><imagedata width="100%" fileref="ObsProject.png"/></imageobject>
            </mediaobject>
        </figure>
        <para>In some cases, the DSA needs to update some of the objects with a certain periodicity.
            These are marked as "DatabaseUpdateable". For example, the WeatherDependenVariables
            class, that contains the Tsys and projected Tsys, is updated for the relevant
            SchedBlocks at the beginning of each DSA iteration. FieldSourceObservability, in the
            other hand, which contains the LST rising and setting time for a source, only needs to
            be updated once, at the beginning of a simulation run.</para>
        <para>The observatory package can be seen in <xref linkend="obs_cd"/>. This section aims to
            represent the state of the telescope hardware throughout the time interval covered by
            the simulation, including the program of array configurations.</para>
        <figure id="obs_cd">
            <title>Observatory package class diagram</title>
            <mediaobject>
                <imageobject><imagedata width="100%" fileref="Observatory.png"/></imageobject>
            </mediaobject>
        </figure>
        <para>The telescope hardware devices are modeled as being either an Assembly, or a
            TelescopeEquipment, which can contain other TelescopeEquipment, and/or Assemblies. This
            hierarchical structure follows the design of the TMCDB.</para>
        <para>Changes in the hardware state are stored as operations over the assemblies or groups
            of assemblies. The actual state of the hardware at a given point in time is dealt with
            following the same design represented by "DatabaseUpdateable". Records are updated
            periodically, following the defined operations.</para>
        <para>An Antenna and a Pad are linked by AntennaInstallation, a link that is time-dependent.
            Several AntennaInstallations conform an ArrayConfiguration. The DSA will start a
            different scheduler for each ArrayConfiguration.</para>
        <para>The weather section is very simple, and is shown in <xref linkend="weather_cd"/>. The
            atmospheric model table is maintained as AtmParameters records, and historical weather
            data is represented as different types of WeatherHistRecords.</para>
        <figure id="weather_cd">
            <title>Weather package class diagram</title>
            <mediaobject>
                <imageobject><imagedata width="100%" fileref="Weather.png"/></imageobject>
            </mediaobject>
        </figure>
        <para>Lastly, <xref linkend="output_cd"/> displays the output package. This package
            includes classes that represent and summarize the results of a simulation. Basically,
            the simulation Results integrate both the Arrays that were created during the simulation
            time, and the ObservationProjects that contained SBs that were executed in the Arrays.
            SB executions are recorded as SchedBlockResult instances.</para>
        <figure id="output_cd">
            <title>Ouput package class diagram</title>
            <mediaobject>
                <imageobject><imagedata width="100%" fileref="Output.png"/></imageobject>
            </mediaobject>
        </figure>
    </sect1>
</article>
